ZAHEER ABBAS

Location: AIC, P.E.C.H.S - 6, Karachi, Pakistan
Cell: +92-317-2065168 | Whatsapp: +966 54 3499087
Email: zaheer.feroz@gmail.com
https://www.linkedin.com/in/zaheer-abbas-a1357824/

ACCOUNTING PROFESSIONAL

Highly analytical and exceptionally skilled professional, offering broad-based years of budgeting, controlling, planning and financial reporting experience in accounting field within fast-paced environment.

Highly dynamic and versatile professional with over 10 years' experience in accounting and finance field by analytical reports, internal auditing, budgeting and cost saving solutions for renowned multinational FMCG company in GCC. Proven success in executing accounting, financial and administrative tasks. Reconciling bank transactions, general ledger, profit/ loss statement & balance sheet in the accounting system to ensure accuracy and reliability of balances. Exceptional communicator with problem resolution, and financial needs assessment aptitude along with identifying opportunities, developing focus and providing tactical business solutions. Languages: English & Arabic

CORE COMPETENCIES

- Asset Management
- Business Analysis
- Cost Saving Initiatives
- Strategy Development
- Communication Skills
- Microsoft Word
- Stock Control

- Financial Analysis & Reporting
- Internal Audit & Control
- Budgeting & Forecasting
- Bank Reconciliation
- Microsoft Excel
- Microsoft PowerPoint
- Bookkeeping

- Financial Accounting
- Cash Flow Management
- Internal Accounting Policies
- Cross-Functional Leadership
- Microsoft Outlook
- Oracle, SAP & ERP
- Payroll Processing

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Spearheaded team of 40 members in accounts/finance, sales, and logistic departments of depot in Afif (KSA).
- Developed, and executed checkpoints process, cost-cutting initiatives, and measures to reduce expiry products.
- Worked on achieving 100% efficiency in cash collection.
- Developed strategies to recover and achieve the misplaced company assets to 100%, also reduced the misuse of assets up to 80% by introducing weekly internal audit process.
- Headed finance team on company policies and daily procedures related to accounts and finance department.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Boom Operations Feb 2019 to Present

MANAGER ACCOUNTS & OPERATIONS

Examine accounting data, summarize financial status, and collect information; issue purchase orders and customer invoices to suppliers and clients. Administer accounts, sales, and logistics operations and formulate financial reports as per prescribed standards to assure record of month and year-end closing provisions in financial statements.

KEY RESPONSIBILITIES

- Lead, manage and monitor accounting functions & over all operations.
- Develop, generate and manage timely accounting reports.
- Ensure reconciliation of Bank accounts and other accounts.
- Monitor general ledger, accounts receivables, accounts payables and other records.
- Create management tools that effectively monitor accounting processes.
- Assist the accounting team in preparing balance sheet and budget reports.
- Generate various analyses and financial reports for the management.
- Monitor and manage the month-end accounting processes.
- Manage budgets for departments, projects and grants.

ZAHEER ABBAS PAGE | 2

- Monitor month-end reports, schedules, payments and receipts.
- Create and monitor an effective internal audit system.
- Ensure timely completion of audit.
- Manage absenteeism, performance, payroll and other related issues.
- Maintain, update and monitor inventory records.
- Ensure compliance of all accounting processes to that of the organization's goals.

Almarai Company, Afif (KSA)

Jan 2015 to Dec 2018

ACCOUNTS OFFICER - MANAGING DEPOT & SALES ACCOUNTS

Examine accounting data, summarize financial status, and collect information; issue purchase orders and customer invoices to suppliers and clients. Administer accounts, sales, and logistics operations and formulate financial reports as per prescribed standards to assure record of month and year-end closing provisions in financial statements.

KEY ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Successfully introduced checkpoints and cost cutting initiatives to reduce expiry products and over expense and achieve 100% efficiency in cash collection.
- Effectively train and direct finance team on company policies related to accounts & finance department, devise strategies, and initiate internal audits to reduce and improve misplaced company assets.

Almarai Company, Duwadme (KSA)

Nov 2011 to Dec 2014

ACCOUNTING OFFICER

Executed accounting, finance, administrative tasks, and reconciled bank statements/transaction in the accounting system to ensure accuracy and reliability of bank account balances. Created and maintained balance sheets, reports, and profit or loss statements, and for monthly and yearly reporting. Examined and formulated reports on department expenses and followed variances from budgeted costs.

KEY ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Played a key role in identifying department level process to improve effectiveness of accounting department.
- Acknowledged with excellence award in 2013 for administering Duwadme Depot and received promotion as Sr. Depot Accountant.

Gerrys Softlogic (Pvt.) Ltd., Pakistan.

Mar 2009 to Jul 2011

SR. ACCOUNTS OFFICER

Delivered excellent, first rate support to the higher management in supervising liquidation process and budgeting of KHI, LHR and ISB branches. Functioned enclose collaboration with accounts department for proper accounting and reporting requirements for new price plans and campaigns.

KEY ACCOMPLISHMENT

 Analyzed gap b/c of obsolete stock items in warehouse and suggested measures to reduce the loss and receive Employee of the Quarter Award twice.

Meezab Pharma (Pvt.) Ltd., Pakistan.

Feb 2003 to Feb 2009

ACCOUNTS OFFICER

Generated accounts receivables information, including monthly statements and ad hoc reports to provide timely information to the stakeholder. Expertly revised accounts processes to ensure best practice and adherence to accounting

standards, policies, and procedures. Oversaw financial operations of the organization to assure timely financial reporting with accuracy also practices including cash management, payroll, financial disbursements, and ledgers.

KEY ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Effectively introduced, developed, and executed inventory control system in company to reduce the loss in stock.
- Controlled and examined sales vs actual expense and described expense analysis reporting for the higher management to take timely decisions.

KEY PROJECTS

- Facilitated the company by working on ISO Certification Archiving Project
- Helped the company by monitoring the Chill project and creating sales analytical reports for 40 customers.
- Monitored project of in-house software and helped in developing modules for accounts/finance, inventory, and sales department.
- Worked on Data Quality Control project at NADRA

EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND

MASTER IN BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION, ACCOUNTS & FINANCE, University of Karachi, 2010

BACHELOR OF COMMERCE, University of Karachi, 2000

CERTIFICATIONS

Staff Training & Development | Conflict Management (2018)

Get Things Done | Change Management | Performance & KPI Management (2017)

Emotional Intelligence (2016)